{"tossups": [{"question": "This man wrote against slavery in one city's <em>Gazette</em> under aliases like \"Vindex\" and \u201cCandidus.\u201d Following the arrival of the <em>Dartmouth</em> this man and James Otis distributed the \"circular letter\" to organize a meeting at Faneuil [[FAN-yoo-il]] Hall. Many years after his best known action, this man succeeded John Hancock to become the fourth governor of Massachusetts. For ten points, name this Founding Father and leader of the Sons of Liberty who orchestrated the Boston Tea Party.", "answer": "<b><u>S</u></b>amuel <b><u>Adams</u></b> (prompt on \u201cAdams\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This polity's ruling family came to power after its scion, Francesco the Malicious, captured its chief fortress while disguised as a Franciscan monk. In 2015, the prince of this polity apologized for its role in the deportation of 90 Jews during the Holocaust. That prince is the child of this country's Prince Rainier III and American actress Grace Kelly. The Grimaldi family has traditionally ruled, for ten points, what wealthy city-state on the Franco-Italian border known for its yearly Grand Prix?", "answer": "Principality of <b><u>Monaco</u></b> (or <b><u>M\u00fanegu</u></b>; or Principaut\u00e9 de <b><u>Monaco</u></b>; or Prin\u00e7ipatu de <b><u>M\u00fanegu</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "According to Pliny the Elder, a red stone named after this deity was able to reflect images. According to Homer in the <em>Odyssey</em>, this deity was \u201cloved more than any place on earth\u201d on the island of Lemnos, which was traditionally the cult center of this god. An altar dedicated to this deity is sometimes referred to by the people of Elis as the altar of \u201cwarlike Zeus.\u201d The Chalceia [[chahl-KAY-ah]] festival, in which \"peplos\" garments were woven from a loom, was dedicated to Athena and this deity. For ten points, what deity was the primary target of worship for Greek blacksmiths and craftsmen?", "answer": "<b><u>Hephaestus</u></b> (or <b><u>Hephaistos</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on \u201cVulcan\u201d)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "A representative from this state was accused in 2021 of violating the Mann Act by transporting a minor across state lines for \"immoral purposes.\" In 2022, this state's governor was caught on film saying \"we gotta stop with this Covid theater\" after children wore masks during a press conference. In March 2022, this state passed a law that barred teaching an elementary school \"LGBT\" curriculum with the \"Don't Say Gay\" bill. For ten points, Matt Gaetz and Ron DeSantis are politicians from what Southern U.S. state?", "answer": "<b><u>Florida</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "A fixture on the Rouen [[roo-EHN]] Cathedral is known as the \"[This Commodity] Tower\" due to having been built by churchgoers who gave up this item up for Lent. Propagandist Joseph Goebbels stated, \"One cannot shoot with [this commodity], but with guns\" in a speech justifying peacetime rationing. A challenge by Napoleon III to invent a substitute for this foodstuff for the poor led to the invention of margarine. Described by Pliny as \"the most delicate of food among barbarous nations,\" for ten points, what is this dairy product made by churning?", "answer": "<b><u>Butter</u></b> (accept <b><u>Butter</u></b> Tower; prompt on \"Dairy\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Teenagers dressed like this man and formed neighborhood gangs in a namesake 1950s subculture in the Belgian Congo. A Beatles song inspired by the \"Bungalow\" version of this man asks him, \u201cWhat did you kill?\u201d In the musical <em>Annie Get Your Gun</em>, this man attempts to persuade Annie Oakley to join his company in the song, \u201cThere\u2019s No Business Like Show Business.\u201d For ten points, what American showman was famed for his cowboy-themed <em>Wild West</em> show?", "answer": "<b><u>Buffalo Bill</u></b> (or William Frederick <b><u>Cody</u></b>; accept <em><b><u>Buffalo Bill</u></b>'s Wild West</em>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "Sailors from this city established the port of Parthenope [[par-THEH-noh-peh]] in Magna Graecia, eventually becoming modern Naples. Ancient theories on why eclipses occur are outlined in <em>The History of Astronomy</em> by Eudemus [[YOO-deh-muss]], a philosopher from this city. Ptolemy III offered to rebuild a bronze statue which collapsed into this city-state's harbor due to a 226 BCE earthquake. For ten points, name this ancient Greek city-state off the coast of Anatolia that possessed a wonder of the ancient world, the bronze Colossus.", "answer": "<b><u>Rhodes</u></b> (or <b><u>Rhodos</u></b>; accept Eudemus of <b><u>Rhodes</u></b>; accept Colossus of <b><u>Rhodes</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The historical \"Sultanate of Women\" period began due to the influence of this man's wife, Roxelana. Despite an overwhelming troop disparity, this man's forces failed to capture the island of Malta in 1565. This man succeeded Selim the Grim and warred with the Safavids under Tahmasp I. This victor at the Battle of Mohacs [[MOH-hahtch]] was later repelled at the 1529 Siege of Vienna. For ten points, identify this sultan of the Ottoman Empire known as \u201cThe Magnificent\u201d", "answer": "<b><u>Suleiman</u></b> the Magnificent (or <b><u>Suleiman</u></b> I; or <b><u>S\u00fcleyman</u></b>-\u0131 Evvel; or <b><u>Suleiman</u></b> the Lawgiver; or \u1e32\u0101n\u016bn\u012b Sul\u1e6d\u0101n <b><u>S\u00fcleym\u0101n</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this kingdom, Savoyard mason Master James of Saint George built a ring of fortifications, including Beaumaris [[boh-mah-REH]], following the passage of the Statute of Rhuddlan. Rhys Gethin [[REES GEH-tihn]] and a national hero of this kingdom, Owain Glendower, defeated the forces of Henry IV at the Battle of Stalling Down. A ruler of this region's kingdom of Powys [[POW-iss]], Llywelyn [[loo-ELL-in]] the Last, swore fealty to Edward I following the English conquest of this modern country. For ten points, name this constituent country of the United Kingdom whose name appears in the Princely title of the heir to the English throne.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Wales</u></b> (or <b><u>Cymru</u></b>; accept Prince of <b><u>Wales</u></b>; accept Kingdom of <b><u>Powys</u> </b>before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Sarah Hopkins Bradford wrote two biographies of this woman, including <em>Scenes</em> <em>From the Life of</em> [this person]. This woman led the forces of James Montgomery in the Raid on the Combahee Ferry during the U.S. Civil War. In 2016, in a decision that was later put on hold, Treasury Secretary Jack Lew announced that this woman would replace Andrew Jackson on the front of the twenty-dollar bill. For ten points, name this abolitionist and Underground Railroad conductor who was known as the \u201cMoses of her People.\u201d", "answer": "Harriet <b><u>Tubman</u></b> (or Araminta <b><u>Ross</u></b>; prompt on \"Moses\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This geographic feature was named after an American who died from a head injury in Panama. A quest to find golden ore led to the immortalization of this feature after a pilot and his companions spent eleven days descending the tepui in order to reach the nearby village of Kamarata. The <em>El R\u00edo Caron\u00ed</em>, a Flamingo monoplane atop Auy\u00e1n-tepui [[ow-YAHN teh-PWEE]] near this geographical feature, was finally recovered more than 30 years after it crashed. For ten points, what geographical feature in Venezuela is the world\u2019s tallest uninterrupted waterfall?", "answer": "<b><u>Angel</u></b> Falls (or Salto <b><u>\u00c1ngel</u></b>; or <b><u>Kerepakupai Ven\u00e1</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "During this war, Leonid Pasternak's charity poster of a wounded soldier leaning against a wall next to the phrase \"Aid to War Victims\" became an anti-war symbol. Alexander Samsonov killed himself after losing the entire Second Army in this war, during which Russia suffered losses at the Masurian Lakes and Tannenberg. The Treaty of Brest-Litovsk withdrew Russia from, for ten points, what war whose devastation led to widespread popular support for the February Revolution?", "answer": "<b><u>World</u></b> War <b><u>One</u></b> (or <b><u>First World</u></b> War; accept the <b><u>Great</u></b> War)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "These things were first theorized by George Johnston Stoney as a \u201cfundamental unit quantity of electricity.\u201d A theory created by John Dalton depicts the water molecule without these particles while a model created by Erwin Schr\u00f6dinger presents these particles as \u201cmatter waves.\u201d Robert A. Millikan\u2019s oil drop experiment was successful in measuring the charge of this particle. Discovered in 1897 by British physicist J. J. Thomson, for ten points, what is this negatively charged particle integral to quantum physics?", "answer": "<b><u>Electron</u></b>s", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {"question": "This man was the third-born child of a group of nobles called the \"Illustrious Generation.\" Cartographers including Jehuda Cresques [[yeh-OO-dah KRES-kess]] and Pedro Nunes [[NOO-ness]] were hired by this man to convene at his alleged School of Sagres [[SAH-gresh]]. This man's personal shield bearer, Gil Eanes [[AINES]], made numerous failed attempted to pass Cape Bojador [[boh-HAH-dor]]. Supposedly sponsoring several expeditions to Madeira and the Azores, for ten points, who was this Portuguese prince known for his attempts to map the west coast of Africa?", "answer": "Prince <b><u>Henry</u></b> the <b><u>Navigator</u></b> (or Infante Dom <b><u>Henrique</u></b>, o <b><u>Navegador</u></b>; accept <b><u>Infante Dom Henrique</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A group of U.S. sailors taken prisoner in this country gave the middle finger in a publicly-distributed photograph, claiming to their captors it was a \"Hawaiian good luck sign.\" This country had the Bauhaus-trained Konrad P\u00fcschel redesign the damaged city of Hamhung. Holding up to 114,000 spectators, this country's Rungrado 1st of May Stadium was the largest stadium in the world until 2020 and featured events such as the Arirang Mass Gymnastics Festival. For ten points, name this Asian peninsular country that fought a war with its southern neighbor in the early 1950s.", "answer": "<b><u>North Korea</u></b> (or <b><u>Democratic People's Republic of Korea</u></b>; or <b><u>DPRK</u></b>; or <b><u>Choson</u></b>-minjujuui-inmin-konghwaguk; prompt on \"Korea\"; do not accept or prompt on \"South Korea\", \"Republic of Korea\", or \"ROK\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Lauzun\u2019s Legion unhorsed Banastre Tarleton during this battle. Wilhelm of the Palatinate-Zweibrucken [[ZVY-broo-ken]] captured Redoubt Number 9 during this battle, while Alexander Hamilton captured Redoubt Number 10. French forces under the Comte de Rochambeau supported American troops during this battle, which led Lord North to proclaim, \u201cOh God, it\u2019s all over.\u201d For ten points, name this last major battle of the American Revolution, which led to the surrender of Charles Cornwallis.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Yorktown</u></b> (accept Siege of <b><u>Yorktown</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This composer's son, Maxim, supported the controversial book <em>Testimony</em>, which Solomon Volkov claimed were this composer's memoirs. A theme from a symphony by this composer, which inspired a song from Franz Lehar\u2019s operetta <em>The Merry Widow</em>, is repeated twelve times to depict a Nazi invasion of his country. An article in <em>Pravda</em> accused this composer of Formalism, after which he wrote his <em>D minor Fifth Symphony</em>. For ten points, name this Soviet composer of the <em>Leningrad Symphony</em>.", "answer": "Dmitri <b><u>Shostakovich</u></b> (or Dmitri Dmitriyevich <b><u>Shostakovich</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This war was declared by one side in part due to a wave of negative publicity toward the concentration camps overseen by a commander known as \"Butcher\" Weyler. Leonard Wood commanded one unit during an assault on Kettle Hill during this conflict, though he was overshadowed by his second-in-command, a former Assistant Secretary of the Navy. For ten points, name this late nineteenth century war during which the Rough Riders captured San Juan Hill, part of a campaign to take Puerto Rico from a European power.", "answer": "<b><u>Spanish-American</u></b> War (or Guerra <b><u>hispano-estadounidense</u></b>; or Guerra <b><u>hispano-americana</u></b>; or Digmaang <b><u>Espanyol\u2013Amerikano</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This scientist worked under John Randall's biophysics unit while on a three-</u><u>year Turner & Newall Fellowship at King's College London. An article titled \u201cThe</u></b> <b><u>Structure of Viruses as (+)</u> Determined by X-Ray Diffraction,\u201d was the last publication of this scientist. Raymond Gosling, a student working under this scientist and Maurice Wilkins, captured </b><em><b>Photo 51</b></em><b>, an image (*) </b>critical in understanding molecular structure. For ten points, name this woman who was influential in discovering the double-helix structure of DNA.", "answer": "Rosalind <b><u>Franklin</u></b> (or Rosalind Elsie <b><u>Franklin</u></b>)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "<b><u>This body of water, home to the Eora and Tharawal people for thousands of</u></b> <b><u>years, is the location to which Maggie May is sent after \u201crobbing a homeward</u></b> <b><u>bounder\" in a Liverpool folk song. Arthur Phillip was assigned to establish a British</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> colony at this location but opted to settle at Port Jackson. James Cook initially referred to this location as \u201cStingrays Harbour,\u201d (*) </b>and this body of water was his first landing site in Australia after sailing from New Zealand. For ten points, what bay in Sydney did the British establish as a penal colony?", "answer": "<b><u>Botany</u></b> Bay (or <b><u>Kamay</u></b>; accept <b><u>Stingrays</u></b> Harbour before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>Many of this artist's surviving illustrations are collected in the Codex Arundel</u></b> <b><u>and the Codex Atlanticus. Giorgio Vasari may have painted over a lost painting by this</u></b> <b><u>artist of four men riding raging war horses during the Battle of Anghiari. Christ (+)</u></b> <b>holds an orb in his left hand in a painting by this artist that sold at auction for $450 million in 2017. This artist likely chose a noblewoman from the Gherardini family as (*) </b>the subject of his one of his best known paintings. For ten points, name this painter of <em>Salvator Mundi</em> and the <em>Mona Lisa</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Leonardo</u><u>da Vinci</u></b> (accept either underlined portion)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's curtailment of the power of the \"Hundred and Four\" who</u></b> <b><u>controlled the</u> </b><em><b><u>Miat</u></b></em><b><u> council led to his exile. After a task force led by Titus Quinctius</u></b> <b><u>[[KWIN-tee-ooss]] Flamininus [[flah-MEE-nee-ooss]] discovered his location in</u></b> <b><u>Bithynia [[bih-THIH-nee-ah]], this general (+)</u> ingested poison according to Livy. Earlier, this brother of Mago won several devastating victories at Lake Trasimene [[trah-see-MEH-neh]] and Cannae [[KAH-nay]] before being defeated during a counter-invasion of (*) </b>North Africa. Scipio's victory at Zama led to, for ten points, which general's defeat in the Second Punic War?", "answer": "<b><u>Hannibal</u></b> Barca", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This author wrote about George Norris's tour of Nebraska in an analysis of his</u></b> <b><u>filibuster of the Armed Ships Bill. Pulitzer Prize-winning journalist Arthur Krock</u></b> <b><u>helped redraft this man's thesis, \"Appeasement At Munich,\" into a book examining</u></b> <b><u>the failures of the (+)</u> British government to take steps to prevent World War Two called </b><em><b>Why England Slept</b></em><b>. In that book by this author, he analyzed figures including Lucius Lamar, Thomas Hart (*) </b>Benton, and Sam Houston. For ten points, name this author who included eight biographies of U.S. senators in his book <em>Profiles in Courage</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>John</u></b> F. <b><u>Kennedy</u></b> (or <b><u>John</u></b> Fitzgerald <b><u>Kennedy</u></b>; or <b><u>Jack Kennedy</u></b>; accept <b><u>JFK</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's time as a barrister included his handling of the \"Caucus Case\"</u></b> <b><u>involving supposedly rigged municipal elections in Bombay. He's not Woodrow</u></b> <b><u>Wilson, but this man proposed his Fourteen Points in response to the Simon</u></b> <b><u>Commission. Stanley Wolpert's biography (+)</u> on this man became the basis for a 1998 biopic which controversially starred Christopher Lee. In the Lahore Resolution, an organization led by this man called for the creation of a (*) </b>Muslim state separate from India. For ten points, name this leader of the Muslim League and founder of Pakistan.", "answer": "Muhammad Ali <b><u>Jinnah</u></b> (or Mahomedali <b><u>Jinnah</u></b>bhai)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>A mass meeting of tenant farmers in this state at the Helderberg Mountains</u></b> <b><u>resulted in the Anti-Rent War, whose leaders were charged with rioting by Amasa J.</u></b> <b><u>Parker. A governor of this state became a leader of the Hunker faction against the</u></b> <b><u>Barnburners and (+)</u> later negotiated the Gadsden Purchase as Secretary of State. A president from this state established a \"Regency\" named for its capital whose members included William Marcy. (*) </b>For ten points, name this state, the birthplace of Martin Van Buren.", "answer": "<b><u>New York</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>After his victory at the Battle of Mount Algidus [[al-GEE-dooss]], a semi-</u><u>mythological character returned to this occupation after a stint as dictator. The</u> </b><em><b><u>Lex</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Manciana</u></b></em><b><u> of North Africa was a 2nd century edict which regulated the maximum</u></b> <b><u>number of (+)</u> tenants in this job and how many days people in this occupation, which included Cincinnatus, needed to (*) </b>plow per month. The writer Columella wrote <em>On</em> <em>Rural Affairs</em> concerning, for ten points, which profession responsible for producing crops?", "answer": "<b><u>Farm</u></b>ers (accept <b><u>Farm</u></b>ing; prompt on \"agriculture\")", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A Labor tax to force Xhosa [[HOH-sah]] men into employment on commercial</u></b> <b><u>farms, called the Glen Grey Act, was passed by this politician while he headed one</u></b> <b><u>colony. A turn-of-the-20th century political (+)</u> cartoon depicts this figure standing over the continent of Africa, representing the prospective Cape to Cairo railway. The modern nations of Zimbabwe (*) </b>and Zambia were once named for, for ten points, what British entrepreneur who names a scholarship that provides a full tuition to Oxford?", "answer": "Cecil John <b><u>Rhodes</u></b> (accept <b><u>Rhodes</u></b> Scholarship)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}